<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>bo kane</title>
    <description>A Jekyll theme for content-rich sites</description>
    <link>/bokane.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="/bokane.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2020 20:12:26 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2020 20:12:26 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sleep</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Progress I’ve made in 2020 towards improving my sleep duration and quality.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;epigraph&quot;&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The best bridge between despair and hope is a good night’s sleep.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;footer&gt;Matthew Walker, &lt;cite&gt; &quot;Why We Sleep: Unlocking the Power of Sleep and Dreams&quot; &lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;I have struggled with sleep now for the better part of a decade.&lt;/span&gt;  I think it started in high school, where I was caught up in a culture of minimizing the importance of sleep. It wasn’t uncommon to stay up late (well past 1 AM) “proving” how dedicated you were to studying. My school tried to combat this by implementing access controls to internet, which were easily circumvented with a VPN. It was not at all unusual to pull all-nighters, and have your roommate begrudgingly attest to your scholarliness the next day at lunch. These habits followed me into college, where I found it impossible to put my mind to rest when it was time to sleep. Over the years, I started developing pretty severe anxiety around sleep. I knew it would take me 1, 2, sometimes 3 hours to actually fall asleep after I went to bed. Knowing there was no way I’d wake up feeling refreshed the following morning would in turn make me anxious about getting done everything I needed to do the following day. Later I started my career at a workplace with pretty intense hours; it wasn’t uncommong to get home after 11pm or midnight on a weekday. Again, I found it difficult to balance this with the need to decompress after work while also juggling the anxiety of knowing I wouldn’t be able to perform at my best the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By late 2019 I was fed up, and some non-sleep related health issues forced me to evaluate what I could do to change my relationship with sleep. Below I outline what I’ve tried so far and how those approaches have worked out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sleep-apnea&quot;&gt;Sleep Apnea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having been told I was a snorer, I signed up for an overnight sleep study at a clinic. Following the study I was diagnosed with moderate obstructive sleep apnea, with an AHI &lt;label for=&quot;1&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;1&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;AHI stands for Apnea-Hypopnea Index, which measures the number of times your breathing pauses for &amp;gt;10 seconds during sleep. Apnea events often result in brief arousals, breaking the continuity of sleep &lt;/span&gt; of 17. I was prescribed a CPAP &lt;label for=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;CPAP stands for continuous positive airway pressure &lt;/span&gt; machine, which I’ve used nightly ever since. The CPAP forces air through my nose at a pressure level that automatically adjusts to my breathing throughout the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I’ve been on this course of treatment for nearly twelve months as I write this, I can’t say it’s been particularly effective at improving the quality or duration of my sleep. I think a part of this may have to do with the fact that CPAP alone didn’t really address my sleep anxiety, which is the biggest driver of sleep duration, which in turn&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;set-and-setting&quot;&gt;Set and Setting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To borrow a catchphrase from Timothy Leary, pre-sleep mind&lt;em&gt;set&lt;/em&gt; and the setting in which I go to sleep contain important variables.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/bokane.github.io/articles/20/sleep</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/bokane.github.io/articles/20/sleep</guid>
        
        
        <category>posts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tiny Habits</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Some mental models I’ve used to hack habit formation.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;I have come to fervently believe in the power of small changes.&lt;/span&gt;  Starting my career in the financial sphere, especially fixed income, I’ve long had an appreciation for the power of compounding interest. The gist is that as you earn interest on some initial principal amount, over time the interest earns interest too, causing the value of your investment (or debt!) to snowball. At even low nominal interest rates, frequent compounding results in huge long term returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though I understood this concept intellectually, in practice I haven’t done a great job applying it outside my career and personal finances. Rather than focus on an easy 1% improvement, I’ve tended to swing for a much harder 10-20% improvement. Changing your habits is &lt;strong&gt;hard&lt;/strong&gt;, and aiming for ambitious outcomes tends to result in failure the majority of the time for me. This results in discouragement and anxiety from failure, which in turn makes me less likely to try again. For a concrete example, several months into the pandemic I noticed I was almost completely sedentary. I would go days without going outside, meaning my only physical activity was going from room to room. To remedy this, I told myself I would start jogging every day for at least 20 minutes. The next morning I get up, lace up my shoes, and hit the pavement. After maybe 5 minutes I’m out of breath and discouraged. I walk home dejected, and can’t help but stress about the failure for the rest of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter tiny habits&lt;label for=&quot;1&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;1&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;NPR’s Life Kit has a great episode on tiny habits &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2020/02/25/809256398/tiny-habits-are-the-key-to-behavioral-change&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;. The three key principles are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(1) Find the smallest version of the habit you want to build toward&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(2) Find a natural cue to start the habit (could be a time, place etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(3) Intentionally celebrate success, e.g. using words of affirmation. As silly as it sounds, this step is absolutely critical.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than tell myself I’m going to jog for 20 minutes every day, I say I’m going to walk around the block just once. Once I’ve taken the first few steps, I start the mental rewards. The idea is to mimic the neural reward system from videogames - the blinking lights, “You Won!” signs etc. which make you want to continue playing. So I fist-pump in the air, give myself positive words of affirmation, and keep going. This approach, unlike the ambitious 20 minute daily jog, is very successful. I find myself excited to wake up and immediately go for a walk in the morning. Virtually every time I go out I end up walking much, much longer than a single block. Even though walking is less impactful than jogging or running from a relative perspective, it’s far more effective on an absolute scale than being ambitious and failing. These improvements also compound over time - I derive happiness from completing the tiny habit, which reinforces my motivation to get up and do it again the next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One difficulty I’ve observed, which I’d love feedback on, is maintaining these tiny habits after disruptions to cues. Maybe my sleep schedule changes, or I have to do something other than walk immediately when I get out of bed which is my normal cue for the walking tiny habit. It’s been really difficult, though not impossible, for me to resume habits when this cue relationship breaks down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another post I’m going to talk about how I’ve applied tiny habits and an experimental approach to hacking my sleep - something I’ve struggled with for going on a decade.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Nov 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/bokane.github.io/articles/20/tinyhabits</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/bokane.github.io/articles/20/tinyhabits</guid>
        
        
        <category>posts</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Foreword</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My first post ends up being a meta-post about setting up the blog.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;It started with footnotes.&lt;/span&gt;  As I thought about my first few blog ideas, I was excited at the prospect of typesetting posts with footnotes. A couple of my favorite authors (Matt Levine, David Foster Wallace) happen to be prolific footnoters. Then I recalled the sidenote styling of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwern.net/index&quot;&gt;Gwern&lt;/a&gt;, and knew my blog wouldn’t be complete until I had it. My writing style tends to be full of  Gwern has a wonderfully detailed section on how the site is constructed, which was my launching point for my own design. My first learning was about static site generators (Gwern uses Hakyll), and decided to go with the Jekyll ecosystem because I’m re-acquainting myself with Ruby for a project that I’m building with Rails. It just so happened someone ported &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/edwardtufte/tufte-css&quot;&gt;Tufte-CSS&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/clayh53/tufte-jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;. I cloned the repository and ran &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll build&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The build fails, and the troubleshooting begins. I try switching Ruby versions first using RVM, then rbenv. Doesn’t work, and later I realize having multiple environment managers is probably an anti-pattern. Looks like it might be a gem versioning issue - uninstalling and reinstalling doesn’t work. I try on another machine entirely - I run into user vs. system install permissioning errors, no dice. This is when I recall I’m in the market for a new computer, so I’ll have to do this again in a few months. I also realize I have probably screwed up the environment for the aforementioned Rails project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I invest the time in setting up a &lt;em&gt;de novo&lt;/em&gt; environment for Jekyll in a virtual machine, then copy the VM from location to location as needed? I start downloading VirtalBox, various Linux images, and get to work. On my ancient Mac Air, VirtualBox is depressingly slow. I start looking at more resource-lite Linux distros. Through Googling, I come across the concept of containerization, e.g. Docker or Kubernetes. After breezing through the official Docker tutorial, I run &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;docker pull jekyll/jekyll&lt;/code&gt; to retrieve the default Docker Jekyll image, and find another well-written &lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.to/michael/compile-a-jekyll-project-without-installing-jekyll-or-ruby-by-using-docker-4184&quot;&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt; on how to compile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/bokane.github.io/assets/img/docker_jekyll_build.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;maincolumn-figure&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time to serve up the site locally. The &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-w&lt;/code&gt; flag allows me to edit my posts in Markdown then refresh the site, so I can update and observe the changes in realtime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/bokane.github.io/assets/img/docker_jekyll_serve.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;maincolumn-figure&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next task is to get my site up on Github Pages to take advantage of Github’s free hosting. Pages dislikes some of the custom Liquid tags in this template; I have to build the site then push it to a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; branch of my repository rather than having Github build Jekyll directly. In the end it is well worth it for the sidenote tags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the greater than anticipated time investment in the technical aspects of setting up my blog, debugging is actually a lot more fun than I recall from my previous romps with programming in high school and college. I had also forgotten the endorphin rush when code compiles/builds correctly - it’s a great feeling!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/bokane.github.io/articles/20/foreword</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/bokane.github.io/articles/20/foreword</guid>
        
        
        <category>posts</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
